Guide to the National Organization for Women, New York City Chapter (NOW-NYC) Records TAM.106
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series X: Our North American Foremothers Documentary, 1970-1984; 5.55 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes, a record carton, a custom box, a flat box, an oversized flat box, and a flat-file-folder
  This series includes materials related to NOW's multimedia documentary, Our North American Foremothers, which was written and produced by Anne Grant. This series includes over 1200 slides depicting historical figures, places, documents, and artifacts from the struggle for women's rights; a 25 page script for the show narrating the history of women's rights and feminism; photographs; correspondence; and ephemera. The series also includes four reels of 16 mm film made for the project by Maria Lessing that were not included in the final project. It should be noted that correspondence about copyright related to the documentary is located in Series II: Correspondence.
  Materials in this series are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - "7252 / Lassing / Harriet Tubman" [small reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34963 (Box 38)
  - "7256 / Lessing" [small reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34964 (Box 38)
  - Correspondence and Promotional Materials, 1972-1973 (Box 145, Folder 16)
  - Documentary Poster (Flat-file-folder 3)
  - "Lessing / first close-ups / Mon / Loretta on the bycicle [sic]" [small reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34966 (Box 38)
  - List of Historical Women, circa 1970-1984 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - "Loretta", [1974]; cuid34962 (Box 38, Reel cuid34962, Box 44, Folder 49)
    The paper materials include one letter describing the production of the film by Maria Lessing for the Foremothers Project.
  - "Loretta and Claudia on the bycycle [sic]" [Small Reel (50 ft.)], [1974]; cuid34965 (Box 38)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 1: 1-14 [1 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 1: 1-14 [2 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 2: 15-30 [1 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 2: 15-30 [2 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 3: 31-44 [1 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 3: 31-44 [2 of 2], undated (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 4: 45-60 [1 of 3], undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 4: 45-60 [2 of 3], undated (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - NOW Slides, Vol. 4: 45-60 [3 of 3], undated (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Option Agreements and Correspondence Slide Show, 1971-1973 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Poster with Press Clippings, undated (Box 91)
  - Script, Cards, and Photographs (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Script Slide Show, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Slideshow Opening Credits [Color Photographs], 1972 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Portrait, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 9)
- Series XI: Audiovisual Materials, 1971-2004; 5.19 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 4 manuscript boxes, a custom box, a cassette box, and 3 unspecified boxes
  This series includes audiocassettes, audio reels, vinyl discs, U-matic tapes, Betamax, and VHS tapes. These audiovisual formats document NOW-NYC protests, conferences, and symposiums; coverage and discussions about the 1984 Presidential election, as well as NOW-NYC elections; NOW-NYC sponsored self-defense classes; and discussions about the Equal Rights Amendment and reproductive rights. This series also includes audiocassettes, reel-to-reel tapes, and film from conferences and radio and television programs from the mid-1970s.
  Missing Materials
  Some recordings in this series are missing as of October 2019, and are therefore not available to researchers.
  Materials are listed in alphabetical order by title.
  - Abortion: The Divisive Issue, undated; cuid45052
    - VHS Tape, cuid45010 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45010)
    - Betamax, cuid45053 (Box 150, Betamax cuid45053)
  - Abortion Meeting #1 and #2, undated; cuid45011 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45011)
  - Abortion Meeting #3, undated; cuid45012 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45012)
  - Choices, undated; cuid45013 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45013)
  - Closing the Wage Gap, October 22, 1985; cuid34472 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34472)
  - Dionysos (NOW), 1971; cuid45014 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45014)
  - Divorce, New York Style, November 27, 1984; cuid34466 (Box 41)
  - Educating Women: With or Without Men, April 9, 1985; cuid34471 (Box 41, U-matic cuid32271)
  - Feminization of Poverty, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, May 28, 1985; cuid34470 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34470)
  - Ferraro 1984, undated; cuid45015 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45015)
  - Gloria Tape, undated; cuid45016 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45016)
  - Insurance, undated; cuid45017 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45017)
  - Legal Abortion But For Whom, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, January 1, 1985; cuid34465 (Box 41)
  - Legal Abortion - But for Whom (Moderator Jennifer Brown) Channel L Working Group, 1985; cuid45018 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45018)
  - Little Bear Training Video (1), undated; cuid45019 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45019)
  - Little Bear Training Video (2), undated; cuid45049 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45049)
  - A Look at the ERA - The Countdown (Ellie Smeal, President NOW), 1981; cuid45020 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45020)
  - March for Women's Lives: March for Freedom of Choice (1), 2004; cuid45021 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45021)
  - March for Women's Lives: March for Freedom of Choice (2), 2004; cuid45050 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45050)
  - Matthea 2nd Anniversary Central Park Attack, undated; cuid45022 (Box 150, Vhs cuid45022)
  - Medical Gr. R., 1980; cuid45023 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45023)
  - Meeting of the Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Jobs, Speaker: Ted Small -- Private Industry Council, 1979; cuid45024 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45024)
  - Metropolitan Avenue, undated; cuid45025 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45025)
  - National NOW Conference Special Interest: Presidential Elections (San Antonio, Texas) (Tape 1), 1980; cuid45026 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45026)
  - National NOW Conference Special Interest: Presidential Elections (San Antonio, Texas) (Tape 2), 1980; cuid45027 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45027)
  - New Worker Orientation to Office Environment Answering Phones, Giving Referrals, undated; cuid45028 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45028)
  - NOW 2000 Conference Organizing Video, cuid45029 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45029)
  - NOW - Central Park Police, Susan B. Anthony, Citi Group, 2000-2001; cuid45030 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45030)
  - NOW Meeting #3 [1/2" open reel video tape], March 22, 1973 (Box 38)
  - NOW Meeting #1 [1/2" open reel video tape], March 22, 1973 (Box 38)
  - NOW-NYC Coverage of Central Park March/"Take Back the Park" March (1), 2000; cuid45031 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45031)
  - NOW-NYC Coverage of Central Park March/"Take Back the Park" March (2), 2000; cuid45057 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45057)
  - NOW-NYC Inauguration, Susan B., NYCLU case, 2000; cuid45032 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45032)
  - NOW NYS Candidates Forum, 2002; cuid45033 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45033)
  - NOW Reel 1, undated; cuid45034 (Box 152, U-matic cuid45034)
  - NOW Reel 2, undated; cuid45035 (Box 152, U-matic cuid45035)
  - NOW "Women And Economic Justice", undated; cuid45036 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45036)
  - One Movement Many Voices N.O.W. and the Women's Movement, 1995; cuid45037 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45037)
  - Opening Ceremony/Keynote Addresses/et al/Part I (NOW Conference), 1991; cuid45038 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45038)
  - Opening Ceremony/Keynote Addresses/et al/Part II (NOW Conference), 1991; cuid45039 (Box Shared Tamiment 207, Audiocassette cuid45039)
  - PAC Presentation, undated; cuid45040 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45040)
  - Poverty Shock: Any Woman's Story, undated; cuid45041 (Box 152, Vhs cuid45041)
  - Promise Keepers, Equality Bashers - National Organization of Women, Inc, 1997; cuid45042 (Box 151, Vhs cuid45042)
  - Rally for Women's Lives Organizing Video, 1995; cuid45043 (Box 152, Vhs cuid45043)
  - Reproductive Rights, April, 1984; cuid34467 (Box 41)
  - The Service Fund of NYC: Model Mugging Basics Class Graduation (1), 1998; cuid45044 (Box 152, Vhs cuid45044)
  - The Service Fund of NYC: Model Mugging Basics Class Graduation (2), 1998; cuid45051 (Box 152, Vhs cuid45051)
  - Sheba Shakespeare, undated; cuid45045 (Box 152, Vhs cuid45045)
  - Susan B. Anthony Awards Tape #1, 1984; cuid45046 (Box 152, Betamax cuid45046)
  - Susan B. Anthony Awards Tape #2, 1984; cuid45047 (Box 152, Betamax cuid45047)
  - Untitled, undated; cuid45048 (Box 152, Betacam cuid45048)
  - "Voter Registration" PSA Videos, 1984
    - Version 1, cuid44424 (Box 42, 1 inch video reel cuid44424)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Duration: 1 min
    - Version 2, cuid44425 (Box 42, 1 inch video reel cuid44425)
      Duration: 2 min
  - When Children are Battleground, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, January 14, 1986; cuid34468 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34468)
  - "Women and Economic Justice" PSA Videos, 1990; cuid44422
    - Master recording with title screen, cuid44428 (Box Shared Tamiment 204, 1 inch video reel cuid44428)
    - Version without title screen, cuid44423 (Box 42, 1 inch video reel cuid44423)
  - Women's Health Issues, Moderated by Jennifer Brown, March 3, 1986; cuid34469 (Box 41, U-matic cuid34469)
- Series XII: Legal Cases, 1970-2025; 1978-1980, 1988-1990; 3.73 Linear Feet in 8 and a half manuscript boxes
  This series contains legal documents that relate primarily to sexual discrimination in the workplace and reproductive rights cases. Legal cases in this series fall into several categories: (1) those where NOW-NYC was directly involved as a plaintiff, as seen in NOW-NYC v. the Department of Defense, et al. and NOW-NYC v. the New York City Police Department; (2) those where NOW-NYC served as a third-party representative for plaintiffs, as seen in NOW v. Pataki and NOW v. Cuomo; (3) those where NOW-NYC provided assistance to plaintiffs, as seen in Rosario v. National Bank of Pakistan and Walmart v. Dukes; and (4) high profile legal cases that NOW-NYC was not directly involved with, but large volumes of flyers, memorandum, correspondence, and press within NOW-NYC was generated supporting the plaintiffs of the case, as seen with Neustein v. Orbach, et al. and Weeks v. Southern Bell Telephone Company. Materials include briefs, plaintiff declarations, memoranda, affirmations, testimony, reports, appeal petitions, press releases, and general correspondence not protected by attorney-client privilege.
  Materials in this series are listed in alphabetical order by case title.
  - Abortion Rights Mobilization (ARM) v. the IRS and Catholic Church, 1980 (Box 145, Folder 17)
  - D'Alessandro v. the New York City Board Of Education, et al., 1995 (Box 145, Folder 18)
  - De Pastino v. the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&T), 1978 (Box 146, Folder 1)
  - Division of Human Rights Lawsuit: National Organization for Women v. Cuomo, 1997-1998 (Box 45, Folder 1-4, Box 148, Folder 5, Box 149, Folder 4)
  - Division of Human Rights Lawsuit: National Organization for Women v. Pataki, 1994-2001 (Box 45, Folder 5-6, Box 156, Folder 1-6, Box 157, Folder 1)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&T), 1970-1972 (Box 146, Folder 2-3)
  - Janney v. Montgomery Ward Co., 1979 (Box 146, Folder 4)
  - Lynch v. Hanold of New York, 1978-1980 (Box 146, Folder 5)
  - Martens v. Smith Barney Inc., 1998 (Box 157, Folder 2-6)
  - National Congress of Neighborhood Women (NCNW) et al. v. the City of New York Department of Employment and U.S. Department of Labor, 1980-1981 (Box 146, Folder 6-8)
  - NOW-NYC v. the Department of Defense, et al., 2023-2025; TW_TAM_106_ER_10
  - NOW-NYC v. the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and American Broadcasting Company (ABC), 1972-1973 (Box 147, Folder 1-4)
  - NOW-NYC v. the New York City Police Department, 1990-1991, 1997 (Box 147, Folder 5)
  - NOW-NYC v. the New York Telephone Company, 1976, 1978 (Box 147, Folder 6)
  - NOW-NYC v. the Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor, 1978-1980 (Box 148, Folder 1-2)
  - New York State Club Association v. the City of New York, the Mayor of New York, and the New York City Human Rights Commission, 1980-1988 (Box 148, Folder 3-4)
  - NOW-NYS v. Terry and Operation Rescue, 1988-1990 (Box 148, Folder 6)
  - Neustein v. Orbach, et al., 1989-1992 (Box 149, Folder 1)
  - People of the State of New York v. Kevin Clarke and Clifford Spencer, 1975 (Box 149, Folder 2)
  - Reinertsen v. Navy Resale Office, 1978 (Box 149, Folder 3)
  - Rosario v. National Bank of Pakistan, 1998 (Box 157, Folder 7-8)
  - Sanstrom v. Rosa, 1994-1996 (Box 149, Folder 4)
  - Walmart v. Dukes, 2011 (Box 149, Folder 5)
  - Weeks v. Southern Bell Telephone Company, 1971 (Box 149, Folder 6)
  - Zangrillo v. Ambach, 1978 (Box 149, Folder 7)
  - Zangrillo, Gold, Negro, and Sica v. the Fashion Institute of Technology (FIT), 1978-1982 (Box 149, Folder 8-9)
- Series XIII: Archived Website, October 2007-ongoing; 2 websites in 2 archived website.
  The NOW-NYC website includes information on the latest news and events regarding NOW-NYC; information about the Women of Power and Influence Awards; their priorities; and ways to get involved. NOW-NYC's priorities include reproductive rights; constitutional equality; LGBTQIA+ rights; promoting diversity; violence against women; and economic and social justice. Crawling of their website began in 2007, and focused on misogyny in media and the Supreme Court decisions to uphold the Federal Abortion Ban. In 2008, a more complete capture of the website was taken and included issues of their newsletter, whatNOW (dating back to 2005); action campaigns related to New York's Reproductive Health Act, the Clinic Access Bill, the Freedom of Choice Act, sex-trafficking, and emergency contraception prices; their political action committee and endorsements; photo galleries from protests; information from their Service Fund; and information from their legal clinics that provide legal assistance and other support regarding discrimination, domestic violence, and other issues. Between 2009-2013, the website contained efforts to support marriage equality, midwifery reform, an Anti-Strangulation Bill, divorce reform legislation, subsidized child care, sexual violence programs, the publication of sex crime statistics, disclosure law for pregnancy service centers, insurance coverage of contraception, equal pay, discriminatory advertising practices, the Reasonable Accommodations for Pregnant Workers Bill, the Violence Against Women Act, and funding for Planned Parenthood. In September 2010, they launched the Take Rape Seriously Campaign. The website also included report cards on how politicians voted on bills supported by NOW-NYC.
  In 2013, the website redesigned and promoted action campaigns related to the Women's Equality Act including: ending sexual harassment in all workplaces, pay equity, pregnancy discrimination, protecting abortion clinics, birth control access, and fighting human trafficking. Between 2014-2017, campaigns included sexual assault in the military; the women's equality agenda; expansion of family court judges; the Burwell v. Hobby Lobby Stores Supreme Court case; untested rape kits; funding for sex-trafficking victims; holding NFL players accountable for domestic abuse; shackling of incarcerated women during childbirth; consent education to schools; the Helms Amendment; ending child marriage; holding police accountable for violence; campaigns against President Trump's cabinet selections; stopping anti-choice legislation; stopping immigration and refugee bans; and increasing birth control access. In 2018, NOW worked in opposition to President Trump's agenda by participating in attempts to prevent the confirmation of Brett Kavanaugh to the Supreme Court; and to increase voting awareness and participation.
  In 2019, the website redesigned to its most recent iteration, as of this writing. Action campaign categories focused on by NOW-NYC include resisting President Trump's agenda; New York City elections; reproductive healthcare and justice; equality and justice; changing laws; and workplace rights. Campaigns through 2022 included holding the NYPD accountable to survivors of sexual assault, mandating sexual education for public school students, ending gun violence, ending abusive practices for home healthcare workers, closing the NY State Intoxication Loophole, and protecting abortion.
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually.